{"question": "What is the definition of a provisional certificate?", "answer": "Character certificate of Intermediate level or 10 +2 6."}{"question": "What is the definition of a provisional certificate?", "answer": "B."}{"question": "What is the meaning of the term labour?", "answer": "Attested copy of Citizenship Labour Law (labour Act 2074): Labour law is concerned over the rights, interests, facilities and safety of workers and employees working in the enterprises of various sectors."}{"question": "What is the meaning of labour?", "answer": "Labour- meaning & importance: \u2022 It is the aggregate of all human physical and mental effort used in the creation of goods and services?"}{"question": "What is the name of the document?", "answer": "Attested copies of Academic Certificates 2."}{"question": "What is the category of engineer?", "answer": "General Engineers - Category A : (Requires Bachelors Degree in Engineering) 2."}{"question": "What is the purpose of the application?", "answer": ") - An application should be submitted to Nepal Engineering Council with applicable fees along with the following documents: 1."}{"question": "What is the definition of Engineer?", "answer": "Professional Engineers - Category B : (Requires Master Degree in approved Engineering field) 3."}{"question": "What is the definition of engineer?", "answer": "Foreign Engineers - Category C : (Non-Nepali engineers willing to work in Nepal, Bachelors Degree in Engineering and minimum 10 years of experience in engineering field."}{"question": "What is the name of the certificate?", "answer": "Character certificate of SLC 4."}{"question": "What is the definition of a engineer?", "answer": "Regulatory Environment in Nepal Nepal Engineering Council (NEC) Act Labour Law (Labour Act 2048) Intellectual Property Right (Copyright Act 2022-2059/ Design Patent & Trade mark act 2052) Building Codes & Bylaws Company Regulation (Company Act 2055/ Private Firm Registration act 2022) Public Procurement Act 2063 &Public Procurement Rules 2064 Arbitration act 2055 (1999) Engineer Licensing Process (According to NEC act): Registration of engineers is done into one of the three categories: 1."}{"question": "What is the definition of a provisional certificate?", "answer": "Intermediate level or 10+2 Transcript 5."}{"question": "What is the name of the certificate?", "answer": "Character certificate of B."}{"question": "What is the meaning of the term \"labour\"?", "answer": "Transcript 8."}{"question": "What is the name of the certificate?", "answer": "Provisional Certificate 7."}{"question": "What is the meaning of the term \"labour\"?", "answer": "9."}{"question": "What is the name of the certificate?", "answer": "SLC mark sheet 3."}{"question": "What is the meaning of the term \"labour\"?", "answer": "E."}{"question": "What is the meaning of the chapter?", "answer": "Chapter 5."}{"question": "What are some of the factories that are examples of seasonal enterprises?", "answer": "Some of the sugar factories are examples of seasonal enterprises."}{"question": "What is the definition of a seasonal enterprise?", "answer": "This also covers: \u2022 Tea state established for commercial purpose \u2022 Enterprises operating within the industrial estate established by government and have less than 10 staff or workers \u2022 Seasonal Enterprises : The enterprises that cannot be operated or which is not feasible to operate all the season, except in a specific season."}{"question": "What is the definition of a major?", "answer": "Major is the person having the age of 18 years and above."}{"question": "Who is the person having final authority on the activities of the enterprise?", "answer": "\u2022 Proprietor : Proprietor is the person having final authority on the activities of the enterprise."}{"question": "What is the definition of an enterprise?", "answer": "Enterprises : It is defined as any factory, organization, institutions, firm or a group established under prevailing laws for the purpose of operation of industry, business or services and having minimum of 10 or more staff or workers."}{"question": "What is the definition of a worker in the construction industry?", "answer": "Labour Act 2074 \u2013 Definition of terminology used: \u2022 Productive process : It means by the following process \u2022 The process of using the goods with the purpose of manufacturing of goods, alterations, repair and maintenance, fabrication, packaging, oiling, washing, cleaning, dismantling, breaking into pieces or use of goods, sales and distribution, transportation or disposal."}{"question": "What is the definition of seasonal enterprises?", "answer": "It also covers the seasonal enterprises that cannot be operated more than 180 days in a year."}{"question": "What are the activities of the workers in the construction industry?", "answer": "\u2022 Pumping of oil, water or sewerage \u2022 Generating, transforming or transmitting energy \u2022 Printing press, lithography, photography, book binding or similar other works?"}{"question": "What was the definition of the term?", "answer": "Before this, there was no special law regarding labour in the construction industry."}{"question": "What is the definition of a worker?", "answer": "Workers are the persons employed on the basis of salary or wages to work in any building, premises, machinery or any part of production process or providing service or any act relating to such works."}{"question": "What is the definition of a minor?", "answer": "\u2022 Minor, Adult : \u2022 Minor is the person having age between 16and 18 years?"}{"question": "What is the meaning of the term workers in the construction industry?", "answer": "There was a trace of interpretation regarding workers in factory and factory workers act 2019."}{"question": "What is the definition of a worker?", "answer": "This also includes any person appointed as the chief of any part or unit of enterprises with power to exercise final responsibility or authority in respect thereof."}{"question": "What is the difference between an employee and a worker?", "answer": "\u2022 Employee and workers : Employees are the persons engaged in administrative functions of the enterprises."}{"question": "What is the definition of a worker?", "answer": "\u2022 Engineer should understand the welfare activities that influence the efficiency of the workers Labour Act 2074 (Obsolete 2048): Labour act 2074 has some special provisions related with construction industry."}{"question": "What is the definition of a worker?", "answer": "This also includes the workers working at piece rate, contract or agreement."}{"question": "What is the minimum amount of leave for workers?", "answer": "Workers are to be provided one-day leave in a week."}{"question": "What is the definition of part time employment?", "answer": "Part time Employment: employment for 35 or less hours in a week."}{"question": "What is the definition of a work-based employment?", "answer": "Labour Act 2074 \u2013 Some important provisions: \u2022 Employment \u2022 Types of employment \u2022 Regular Employment, \u2022 Work Based Employment: for completion of certain work or rendering certain service, \u2022 Time Bound Employment: employment for certain time period determined, \u2022 Casual Employment: employment for seven or less days in a month,?"}{"question": "What is the definition of a working hour?", "answer": "\u2022 Prohibition on employment without employment contract \u2022 Formation of employment relationship \u2022 Probation period \u2022 Trainee & Apprentices \u2022 Trainees may be hired Applicability of labour provision \u2022 May be employed as apprentices \u2022 Part time Workers \u2022 Work Permits \u2022 Restriction on employment of foreign nationals \u2022 Requirement of work permits for foreign nationals to work in Nepal \u2022 Works permit may be issued \u2022 Language of the agreement \u2022 Repatriation of remuneration in convertible foreign currency \u2022 Remuneration, employment conditions and benefits and other provisions for foreign workers \u2022 Working Hours o Working hours * Maximum 8 hours a day or 48 hours a week has been fixed as working hour."}{"question": "What is the meaning of remuneration?", "answer": "\u2022 Remuneration : Means the salary or wage to be received in cash or kind from the enterprise by the worker or employee for the works performed in the enterprise and this waord shall also include any amount to be received in cash or kind for the works done under piece rate or contract."}{"question": "What is the definition of overtime?", "answer": "In any enterprise, where works have to be carried out continuously without interruption, such breaks shall be provided on rotation basis \u2022 Extra wage for overtime works * Workers or employee (staff) shall be provided extra remuneration for the overtime work working more than 8 hours a day or 48 hours a week * Workers shall be paid one and half of the ordinary wage for the overtime work."}{"question": "How long should workers be allowed to work?", "answer": "Workers shall be provided with 30 minutes break (interval) for tiffin and rest."}{"question": "What is the definition of overtime?", "answer": "However, no workers or staff shall be forced to work overtime."}{"question": "What is the definition of remuneration?", "answer": "\u2022 Computation of beginning of working hour * The time for starting work shall be as prescribed by the proprietor \u2022 Interval for refreshment and rest * No workers shall be kept working continuously for more than 5 hours."}{"question": "What is the difference between regular working hour and overtime?", "answer": "This break is also counted in regular working hour."}{"question": "What is the minimum remuneration for the workers?", "answer": "space."}{"question": "How much space is provided to the worker?", "answer": "Light and temperature * In managing waste disposal * For cleaning all the foul dust, air, vapour any other foul substances that may cause hazard to health * For making necessary arrangement to prevent loud noise from any source * A worker shall be provided 15cu."}{"question": "What is the responsibility of the manager of an enterprise?", "answer": "\u2022 Remuneration \u2022 Minimum remuneration fixing committee \u2022 Payment of remuneration \u2022 Period of remuneration \u2022 Prohibition on deduction of salary \u2022 Petition against undue deduction or delay in payment \u2022 Provision of appeal \u2022 Leave \u2022 Weekly holiday \u2022 Public holiday \u2022 Substitute leave \u2022 Home leave \u2022 Sick leave \u2022 Maternity leave/mourn leave/accumulative leave Provident fund, gratuity and Insurance \u2022 Contribution for provident fund \u2022 Right to receive gratuity \u2022 Provision of medical insurance \u2022 Provision of accidental insurance \u2022 Health and safety o Provisions relating to health and safety: Manager of an enterprise is responsible * In keeping clean the working place * In managing sufficient air."}{"question": "How many cubic meters of space is required for a worker?", "answer": "m."}{"question": "What is the minimum remuneration for an enterprise?", "answer": "* In general, no workers or staff shall be allowed to work overtime for more than 4 hours a day or 24 hours in a week \u2022 Attendance register to be kept * Each enterprise shall keep attendance register of its workers and employees."}{"question": "What are some examples of what type of companies?", "answer": "For example, you can identify the products of Nike Inc."}{"question": "What is the definition of a copyright?", "answer": "As time lapses, the work can be republished or reproduced by others."}{"question": "What is the definition of a trademark?", "answer": "A trademark can be a combination of words, phrases, symbols, logos, designs, images or devices, used by an individual, legal entity or business organization to distinguish their products from that of others."}{"question": "What type of intellectual property is categorized?", "answer": "As stated earlier, intellectual property is categorized into various types as per the nature of work."}{"question": "What are the types of intellectual property?", "answer": "The artistic works come under the category of copyright laws, while the commercial ones, also known as industrial properties, are ruled by patents, trademarks and industrial design rights."}{"question": "How long does the right last?", "answer": "In case of anonymous works, the right lasts for 95 years after publication or 120 years after the creation."}{"question": "What is the definition of a copyright?", "answer": "The right lies with the owner-cum-copyright holder for a certain period of time."}{"question": "What are the types of legal action that can be taken against the owner of the work?", "answer": "Otherwise you can initiate legal action against such persons."}{"question": "What are the types of trademarks that are protected?", "answer": "Once registered, trademarks are protected legally and the owners can sue persons who use their trademarks."}{"question": "What are the types of intellectual property that are governed by?", "answer": "Copyright laws deal with the intellectual property of creative works like books, music, software, painting, etc."}{"question": "What is the difference between the two types of intellectual property?", "answer": "The work can be either artistic or commercial."}{"question": "What is the definition of a right?", "answer": "Such a right is called intellectual property."}{"question": "What are the types of intellectual property rights?", "answer": "\u2022 Special provisions to be applicable to special type of enterprise o Tea state o Construction business * Provision for construction tools * Special arrangement at temporary construction sites * Accident insurance * Safety arrangements o Transportation business o Tourism related business Conduct and punishment \u2022 Committee, officers and other provisions \u2022 Settlement of labour disputes \u2022 Miscellaneous Intellectual Property Rights Intellectual property is a right you have on your creations, like a film, a musical composition, an invention, a brand name, etc."}{"question": "What are the types of intellectual property?", "answer": "If you have an intellectual property (IP) over any of your work or ideas, others need to take your permission before using it."}{"question": "What is the definition of intellectual property?", "answer": "Intellectual property refers to the right over the intellectual work and not the work itself."}{"question": "What are the types of intellectual property?", "answer": "Industrial properties cover those created and used for industrial or commercial purposes."}{"question": "What is the definition of intellectual property?", "answer": "Like any other real property, you have the right to own and protect the creations of your mind."}{"question": "What are the most common types of intellectual property?", "answer": "The most common types of intellectual property are copyrights,trademarks,patentsandindustrialdesignrights."}{"question": "How long does a copyright last?", "answer": "Usually, the timespan of a copyright extends through the entire life of the owner and lasts up to a period of about 50 to100 years after death."}{"question": "What is a trademark?", "answer": "Trademarks A trademark is a symbol, which is generally used to identify a particular product, which indicates its source."}{"question": "What is a copyright?", "answer": "Copyrights A copyright is a right conferred on the owner of a literary or artistic work."}{"question": "What is the name of the company?", "answer": ", through their logo, which is embossed on their products."}{"question": "What is a copyright?", "answer": "It is an exclusive right to control the publication, distribution and adaptation of creative works."}{"question": "What are patents?", "answer": "Patents are rights related to new inventions."}{"question": "What is the definition of a patent?", "answer": "The person who receives a patent for his invention has an exclusive right to control others from making, using, selling, or distributing the patented invention without permission."}{"question": "What is the definition of a patent?", "answer": "It can refer to the creation of a shape, color, pattern or a combination of all these things."}{"question": "What is the time limit of a patent?", "answer": "Generally, the time limit of a patent is 20 years from the date of filing the application (for the patent) Industrial Design These rights also come under intellectual property and protect the visual design of objects that are not purely utilitarian, but have an aesthetic or ornamental value."}{"question": "What is the definition of an invention?", "answer": "It can be an industrial commodity or a handicraft."}{"question": "How long is a patent?", "answer": "The right is conferred for a period of 10 to 25 years."}{"question": "What are the requirements for a patent?", "answer": "In general, the invention must be new, inventive and should be useful or can be applied in industries."}{"question": "What is the definition of patent?", "answer": "This right is conferred on persons who invent any new machine, process, article of manufacture or composition of matter, biological discoveries, etc."}{"question": "What is the definition of a patent?", "answer": "The integrity of the work shall be maintained unchanged unless the author gives explicit permission."}{"question": "What is the definition of an industrial design right?", "answer": "An industrial design right is conferred after considering factors like, novelty, originality and visual appeal."}{"question": "What are the basic rights of a patent?", "answer": "\u2022 Attribution (Credited) and integrity (Unchanged): The author of the work has the right to have his name attributed to the work when it is published, quoted or otherwise displayed."}{"question": "What are the three basic areas of copyright?", "answer": "The concept of copyright can be broken down into three basic areas."}{"question": "What is the definition of a copyright?", "answer": "Subject to provision of copyright act, copyright exist in every original literary, dramatic, musical and artistic work."}{"question": "What is the definition of a design?", "answer": "The design can be either two-dimensional (based on pattern, colors and lines) or three-dimensional (as per shape and surface)."}{"question": "What are the criteria for a patent?", "answer": "In order to grant a patent, the invention should fit into the following criteria, which may differ from country to country."}{"question": "What is the definition of a copyright?", "answer": "Copyright: (Copy right act 2022 has been repealed and Copyright act 2059 prevail) Copyright generally means the sole right to produce or reproduce the work or any substantial part thereof in any material form whatever."}{"question": "What is the basic principle of copyright?", "answer": "The basic principle of copyright is that a person or a group of people has the sole right of physical and intellectual ownership to any work that is in it a \u201cunique work of art\u201d created by the person or a group of people."}{"question": "What is the definition of a patent?", "answer": "The person who has an industrial design right has the exclusive right to make or sell any objects in which the design is applicable."}{"question": "What is the provision regarding copyright?", "answer": "Provision regarding license of copyright: \u2022 Grant of license of copyright holder: Incase any owner of the copyright grants license to publish whole or part of such work, the licensee shall be entitled to publish suck work in accordance with the conditions of the license only."}{"question": "What are the basic aspects of responsibility for a unique work?", "answer": "Having created a unique work, two elementary aspects of responsibility follow specially in situations where conflicting claims need to be resolved."}{"question": "What are the rights associated with unique creativity in performance interpretation and display?", "answer": "\u2022 Display and performance: Rights associated with unique creativity in performance interpretation and display."}{"question": "What are the main aspects of compensation for lost income?", "answer": "\u2022 Income and compensation: There are numerous examples of vast sums being awarded in compensation for lost income because a work has been illegally copied and distributed."}{"question": "What is the definition of the term copyright?", "answer": "Ownership of copyright and his rights : \u2022 Acquisition of ownership of copyright: Any person registering any of his work shall have the copyright in accordance with the provision of copyright act."}{"question": "What is the definition of the term copyright?", "answer": "\u2022 Transfer of copyright: The person having the right to register the copyright may transfer with or without any conditions, his right, wholly or partially, to another person."}{"question": "What is the statutory term of the copyright?", "answer": "Notice to be given of the transfer of copyright Registration of copyright and his rights : Any person who desires to register any work shall apply to the office of the registrar giving such particulars as have been prescribed together with evidence of his ownership in such copyright; such application shall accompany the prescribed registration fee."}{"question": "What is the definition of the term copyright?", "answer": "\u2022 Grant of license by registrar: Incase any work, which has once been published for the public, is required in the interest of public to be published again, and the owner of the copyright fails to publish and also refuse to grant permission to any other person for such publication, the registrar may grant license to any other person."}{"question": "What is the common practice of the professions to retain insurance policies in case of professional negligence?", "answer": "It is quite normal for many professions such as law, medicine, engineering and the journalistic media to retain insurance policies in case of claims against professional negligence."}{"question": "How long does the copyright last?", "answer": "Term of copyright The copyright in any work subsists during the lifetime of the author and shall continue for fifty years after his death."}{"question": "What is the definition of legal liability?", "answer": "Legal liability: Claims for offensive creation such as defamation of character, personal injury, lost income and infringement of copyright etc."}{"question": "What is the definition of what type of rights a person has in a work?", "answer": "?"}{"question": "What is the main reason for the use of copyright?", "answer": "\u2022 Ownership, reproduction and distribution: For technical and economic reasons it has been customary for authors to share the rights of commercial exploitation or their work with publishers either by employment or contract."}{"question": "Who has the right to have the copyright of any work registered?", "answer": "The right to have the copyright of any work registered shall vest only in the author of the work except few conditions."}{"question": "What is the statutory remedy for the loss caused to the copyright owner by the inf?", "answer": "Compensation for the loss caused to the copyright owner by the infringer of the protected right shall also be realized and provided to the copyright owner."}{"question": "What are the rights that relate to patents, trademarks, design?", "answer": "Industrial property right (Patent, Trademark, Design) Rights that relate generally to patents, trademarks, copyrights and industrial design are sometimes called industrial property rights."}{"question": "What is the purpose of the publication?", "answer": "\u2022 Fair and necessary publication of any work in connection with private study, research, criticism, review and any act in connection with news and magazines, radio diffusion and court proceedings; or \u2022 Any publication of an expert from an unpublished work made with bona fide intention of using it for an academic institutions and which clearly indicates in its title the purpose of using it for an academic institutions and the description of author \u2022 No person shall sell or distribute or give on hire or arrange any show or keep it in possession for any other similar purpose or publicize or broadcast it in any manner knowing fully well or having sufficient reason to believe that any publication is unauthorized publication."}{"question": "What is the definition of a publication?", "answer": "Unauthorized publication and punishment: \u2022 Any publication which has been made without the license of the owner or without license from the registrar, for monetary gain shall be deemed to be an authorized publication."}{"question": "What is the punishment for a person who infringes on a protected right?", "answer": "Punishment : In cases where any person infringes protected right, such person shall be punished with a fine of a sum from ten thousand to one hundred thousand rupees or imprisonment for a term not exceeding six months or both and with a fine of a sum from twenty thousand to two hundred thousand rupees or imprisonment for a term not exceeding one year or with both for each instance from the second time."}{"question": "What is the definition of a copy of a work?", "answer": "Any importation of a single copy made for personal use shall not be deemed to be contravention of this section."}{"question": "What is the license for public exhibition?", "answer": "\u2022 License of public exhibition: Registrar may grant general or special license for public exhibition after specifying the necessary conditions."}{"question": "What rights are governed by the Patent, Design and Trademark Act 2022?", "answer": "The Patent, Design and Trademark Act 2022 govern these rights."}{"question": "What is the license for translation?", "answer": "\u2022 License of public library: Registrar may, for the purpose of keeping such copy in the library, grant license for the reproduction of whole or any specified portion of the work."}{"question": "What is the license for translation?", "answer": "\u2022 License for translation: Publication of translation of work rendered into Nepali may grant such license provided that such license shall not be deemed to bestow sole ownership on the translator."}{"question": "What is the statutory definition of a publication?", "answer": "Provided that any publication made in the following circumstances shall not be deemed to be an unauthorized publication."}{"question": "What is an important invention?", "answer": "Patent: \u2022 It is an important invention of any theory, principle or formula \u2022 An invention regarding to technology or process on the structure of matter or group of matters?"}{"question": "What is the definition of a patent?", "answer": "\u2022 Ownership of a patent can be transferred in any way to any person as movable property \u2022 If anybody does or attempt to do so or encourage to do any work against these rights of patentee may be punished with a fine by the order of concerned department and all the materials related with such offence shall be confiscated."}{"question": "What are the conditions of acquiring patent right?", "answer": "\u2022 Name, address and profession of inventor \u2022 In the case of invention not invented by the applicant himself, the conditions acquiring such right from inventor by the applicant."}{"question": "What is the definition of a patent?", "answer": "Application for acquiring patent right: Person willing to acquire patent right in his own name shall have to apply to the concerned department with following information including all other evidence."}{"question": "What is an invention of new way of operation and dissemination?", "answer": "An invention of new way of operation and dissemination."}{"question": "What is the requisite fee for a patent?", "answer": "Drawings and sketch o invention (if necessary) \u2022 Prescribed application fee as mentioned in schedule."}{"question": "What is the definition of patent?", "answer": "\u2022 Any patent registered in the name of any person shall not be copied, used or utilized without the patentee\u2019s written consent."}{"question": "What is the definition of patent?", "answer": "\u2022 Method of operation or utilization of such invention \u2022 Principle or formula, if such patent is based on any principle or formula?"}{"question": "What is the definition of patent?", "answer": "Right over the Patent (Acquisition of patent right): \u2022 Any person, willing to have rights on any patent, has to register such patent under the Patent, Design and Trademark Act."}{"question": "What is the Term of Patent?", "answer": "\u2022 If concerned authority found the patent application is patentable after examination, provides certificate to the applicant \u2022 Applicant shall pay a registration fee as prescribed in price schedule Publication of registered patent: \u2022 Concerned authority shall publish all patents, except those to be kept secret o national interest in journal (media) \u2022 Anybody willing to see or take a copy of the statement, drawing or sketch of a patent published in journal may see or take a copy of such patent document on payment of a fee as prescribed in schedule Opposition: \u2022 If anybody has any complain upon any patent, he may lodge such complains to the concerned department within thirty-five days from the date on which the patent is seen or a copy of such patent document is taken \u2022 Upon receipt of the complain, concerned authority take necessary action through an investigation Term and renewal: \u2022 Patentee shall have his right on the patent for a period of seven years from the date of registration \u2022 The patentee shall renew the patent within the 35 days from date of expiry having paid the fee mentioned in schedule \u2022 Renewal of patent may be made for two times of seven years Design:Any design, form or shape of materials made through the preparation by any method Right on Design (Acquisition of design right): \u2022 Anybody may have a right on design of any goods under the act, which is made or caused to be made by him, and has been registered in concerned authority \u2022 Ownership of a design can be transferred \u2022 Nobody shall make any goods by using other\u2019s design or in a way to manipulate the people in general and copying such design without written consent of the person in whose name, design is registered."}{"question": "What is the definition of trademark?", "answer": "\u2022 Concerned authority also looks whether the design to be registered is new and original Registration of design: \u2022 The concerned department after examination of any application shall register the design in the name of applicant \u2022 The applicant shall pay prescribe registration fee to the concerned department to obtain the certificate of registration Term and renewal of design: \u2022 The design holder shall have his right on the design for a period of five years from the date of its registration \u2022 The design holder shall renew the registration of the design within 35 days from the date of expiry Penalty to the violator: \u2022 If anybody violates the rights of registered design holder may be punished with a fine by the order of the concerned department and all the goods related with such offence shall be confiscated Trademark: \u2022 It is any word, symbol or picture or the combination of the three used for showing difference from goods or service of others to the goods produced by any firm, company or individual or the service provided by it."}{"question": "what is the difference between a patent and a design?", "answer": "Particulars Copyright Patent Design Trademark 1 Subject matter/covera ge Rights relate to work of authorship/literary work /artistic work- music, book,movie/painting/photos Rights relate to new inventions/theory/pri nciples/process/formu la Rights relate to shape, pattern, color of commodities, product Rights related to word, symbol, picture, figure or combination of all these to recognize goods."}{"question": "what is the difference between copyright, patent, design and trademark?", "answer": "N."}{"question": "what is the difference between copyright and trademark?", "answer": "Comparison Chart between copyright, patent, design and trademark S."}{"question": "What is the purpose of building rules?", "answer": "For fulfilling this purpose Building act 2055(1998) was promulgated (circulated) and meantime Building rules 2062(2005) was also come into operation."}{"question": "What is the governing act of the building code?", "answer": "0) 1000,7000, (1000,2000) 1000,5000 8 Governing act Copyright act 2059 Patent, design and trademark act 2022 Patent, design and trademark act 2022 Patent, design and trademark act 2022 Building Act, codes and bylaws Regulating building construction activities was essential for the purpose of keeping building safe from earthquake, fire and other natural calamities."}{"question": "What are the building rules?", "answer": "With reference to building rules, building are to be constructed following National Building Code 2060."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building?", "answer": "5 m with NBC 105 NBC 111 NBC 208 shapes NBC 106 NBC 112 3 Mandatory Rules of Thumb Buildings of plinth area less than 1,000 sq."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building code?", "answer": "5m and regular less and constructed by technicians in the areas where professional engineer\u2019s service is not available 4 Guidelines of Remote Rural Buildings (Low Strength Masonry/ Earthen Buildings) Buildings constructed by local masons in remote areas and not more than 2 stories NBC 000 categorizes design and construction of buildings into four types according to their level of sophistication."}{"question": "What is the main thrust of the code?", "answer": "(Classification of building codes) a) International state of art The major thrust of the code is aimed at the typical and most common buildings currentlybeing constructed in Nepal."}{"question": "What is the purpose of the code?", "answer": "NBC 206: 2003 Architectural Design Requirements NBC 207: 2003 Electrical Design Requirements for (Public Buildings) NBC 208: 2003 Sanitary and Plumbing Design Requirements Classification of NBC according to their use SN Type of Building Code Purpose 1 International State-of-Art Applicable to large building structures."}{"question": "What type of building codes are applicable to Nepal?", "answer": "ft."}{"question": "What is the main thrust of the code?", "answer": "It does not suggest as being practical for everyday considerationthe sophisticated design philosophies and analytical techniques that appear in the buildingcodes of developed countries."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building?", "answer": "ft, Applicable codes: NBC 201, Building having stories less than 3, shape NBC202, NBC 205 building having span less than 4."}{"question": "What type of building codes are applicable to Nepal?", "answer": ", buildings having more than 3 stories, irregular NBC 104 NBC 110 NBC 207 buildings with span more than 4."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building code?", "answer": "Under the first category International State-of-the-Art, ifconsultants ensure that their designs meet the corresponding international standard, thedesigns are considered to be in conformity with NBC."}{"question": "What is the definition of NBC 000?", "answer": "The Applicable codes: NBC 000 structures must comply with existing international state-of-the-art building codes 2 Professionally Engineered Buildings Applicable codes:NBC 101 NBC 107 NBC 113 Building designed and constructed under supervision than NBC 102 NBC 108 NBC 114 of engineers, buildings with plinth area more NBC 103 NBC 109 NBC 206 1000 sq."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building?", "answer": "Building having plinth area more than 1000 S."}{"question": "What is the definition of a simple building?", "answer": "Simple buildings that are constructed, where professional engineers and technicians are not available, under supervision of middle level technicians of which plinth area is less than 1000 Sq."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building of restricted size?", "answer": "ft."}{"question": "What are the requirements for a rural building?", "answer": "In the form of diagrams anddescriptions aimed at technical advisors, house owners and lay-men, these guidelinesemphasize those changes that should be made to current practices to improve the seismicresistance of these buildings not subject to modern quantitative analysis and rational designconsideration."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building?", "answer": "The explanatory documents are such that an experienced overseer will be able to understandthem and present sufficient details at the time of permit application to prove to a skilledappraiser at the Local Authority that the requirements have been met."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building of restricted size?", "answer": "5 m which will be constructed under design and supervision of engineer fall in this category."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building of restricted size?", "answer": "c) Buildings of restricted size designed with simpleRules-of-Thumb - Mandatory rules of thumb (MRT) It refers to Buildings of restricted size designed with simple Rules-of-Thumb, and mostly applies to remote areas where simpler buildings are prominent."}{"question": "What is the definition of a typical rural building?", "answer": "It covers all usual structures such as hospitals,meetings halls, factories, warehouses, multi-storey buildings and residential buildings."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building of restricted size?", "answer": ", more than 3 storied and structural span of more than 4."}{"question": "What is the definition of a mandatory building?", "answer": "Whereas these recommendations aredescribed as guidelines, it is intended to be mandatory for such structures built in areascontrolled by a building permit-issuing local authority."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building of restricted size?", "answer": ", less than 3 storied and structural span less than 4."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building of restricted size?", "answer": "g."}{"question": "What types of building are normally of earthen construction?", "answer": "unburned masonry,mud-mortar, rubble, dry stone, wattle and daub)."}{"question": "What type of building is normally of earthen construction?", "answer": "These structures are normally of earthen construction (e."}{"question": "What are the guidelines for rural buildings?", "answer": "d) Guidelines for remote rural building These guidelines addressabout a dozen typical building styles that have been condensed from an inventory ofapproximately fifty-five building types surveyed in 1993."}{"question": "What are the requirements for a building of restricted size?", "answer": "The requirements are interms of limits on spans and heights, minimum reinforcing and member sizes, positioning ofearthquake-resisting elements and other such rules."}{"question": "What is the definition of a building of restricted size?", "answer": "5 m fall in this category."}{"question": "What are the requirements for a building under this category?", "answer": "NBC 201,202 and 205 are applicable for buildings under this category and the codes deals with Mandatory Rules of thumb (MRT) reinforced concrete building with masonry infill, mandatory rules of thumb load bearing masonry and MRT reinforced concrete building without masonry infill respectively."}{"question": "What are the requirements of building codes?", "answer": "It specify the minimum acceptable level of safety for constructed objects such as buildings and non- building structures."}{"question": "What is a right of way?", "answer": "A right of way is a type of easement granted or reserved over the land for transportation purposes, such as for a footway, carriageway, trail, driveway, rail line or highway."}{"question": "What are the main objectives of building bylaws?", "answer": "Building bylaws are prepared to ensure public health and safety, planned urban development and planned built environment."}{"question": "Who is required to have building permission?", "answer": "Similarly, it is also mandatory to have building permission from concerned valley Development Corporation, urban development office, metropolitan or sub metropolitan city, municipal office."}{"question": "What are the guidelines for building construction?", "answer": "In the case of an easement, it may revert to its original owners if the facility is abandoned."}{"question": "What are the main objectives of building bylaws?", "answer": "With rapid growing urbanization and increase in population, it becomes an important tool & mechanism for the controlling of growth and development of the cities."}{"question": "What is a right-of-way?", "answer": "A right-of-way is reserved for the purposes of maintenance or expansion of existing services with the right-of-way."}{"question": "What are the requirements of building codes & bylaws?", "answer": "Building codes & bylaws provide the regulations and standards that architects, builders and owners must meet while designing, constructing or remodeling buildings."}{"question": "What are the guidelines for building construction?", "answer": "These are prepared by concerned town development committees and are followed by the municipalities of the country."}{"question": "What are the objectives of building bylaws?", "answer": "Objectives of bylaws \u2022 To design & construct the building as per climatology, topography, acoustic & thermal aspect \u2022 To develop necessary physical infrastructure \u2022 To use new land for future expansion \u2022 To maintain & show civilization \u2022 To create comfort living standards \u2022 To conserve & develop socio economic, cultural, architectural & historical values Basic components of building bylaws a) Building b) Planning c) Enforcement Elements of the building bylaws in Building segment \u2022 Right of Way(ROW) A right-of-way is a right to make a way over a piece of land, usually to and from another piece of land."}{"question": "What are the NBC codes for earthquake resistance building construction?", "answer": "Simple buildings having less than two storied that are constructed in remote rural areas, where control is impractical because of non-availability of regular technical supervision fall under this category and implemented NBC codes are as mentioned below: NBC 203 : Guidelines for earthquake resistance building construction: Low strength masonry NBC 204 : Guidelines for earthquake resistance building construction: Earthen building Building act has directed to comply with the building codes while constructing a building by any persons, institutions or public entities."}{"question": "What are the building bylaws?", "answer": "Building bylaws It is the set of guidelines regarding the design of buildings, orderly and systematic planning of the area and ensure safety standards."}{"question": "What is the definition of a setback?", "answer": "Ignorance of law will not be excused."}{"question": "Where are setbacks set?", "answer": "Setbacks are generally set in municipalordinances or zoning."}{"question": "What are the different types of hazards that might be regulated?", "answer": "Depending on the jurisdiction, other things like fences, landscaping, septic tanks, and various potential hazards or nuisances might be regulated."}{"question": "What is the definition of a setback?", "answer": "Law : It is the norms that are drafted and enforces by a state or local government in order to regulate the activities within the state or locality."}{"question": "What is the definition of a setback?", "answer": "The terms can also refer to limits imposed on such a ratio."}{"question": "What is the definition of a setback?", "answer": "As a formula: Floor area ratio = (total covered area on all floors of all buildings on a certain plot)/(area of the plot) \u2022 Ground Coverage Ratio(GCR) \u2022 Height of the building \u2022 Guidelines for cultural heritage zone \u2022 Clearance required for important sites and from other elements Elements of Building bylaws in Planning segment \u2022 Land use \u2022 Size of the plot \u2022 Area and its depth and width ratio \u2022 Length of cul-de-sac (impasse/dead end) \u2022 Area of open space \u2022 Public facility requirement Elements of Building bylaws in Enforcement process segment \u2022 Designing of building stages \u2022 Construction stage \u2022 Issuance of completion certificate \u2022 Use of constructed facility Business Law: Business : It is the human activities that are related with production of goods and services or sales and purchase of goods and services or exchange of goods and services with profit making objectives."}{"question": "What is the definition of a setback?", "answer": "\u2022 Floor Area Ratio(FAR) Floor area ratio (FAR), floor space ratio (FSR), floor space index (FSI), site ratio and plot ratio are all terms for the ratio of a building's total floor area to the size of the piece of land upon which it is built."}{"question": "What is the definition of business law?", "answer": "All the laws that regulate the business are known as business law."}{"question": "What is the definition of a setback?", "answer": "\u2022 Set Back In land use, a setback is the distance which a building or other structure is set back from a street or road, a river or other stream, a shore or flood plain, or any other place which is deemed to need protection."}{"question": "What is the type of business organization registered under?", "answer": "This type of business organization is registered under partnership Act 2020."}{"question": "What is the definition of a partnership business?", "answer": "Limitation of partnership business: \u2022 Unlimited liability \u2022 Uncertain existence \u2022 Possibility of misunderstanding and friction between the partners \u2022 Limited capital \u2022 Difficulty in transferring ownership \u2022 Lack of prompt decision \u2022 Lack of public faith Company business organization: In this type of business organization, company is established under the Act of the country and has limited liability."}{"question": "What is the principle of equity in a company?", "answer": "Finance is collected through issuance of shares."}{"question": "What is the definition of a private limited company?", "answer": "As per company Act 2053, private limited company has less than 50 shareholders and public limited company shall have minimum 7 shareholders and no upper limit."}{"question": "What is the main difference between private and public business?", "answer": "\u2022 Principal of equity \u2022 Statute of legislature \u2022 Custom and usage \u2022 Nepalese statutory act \u2022 Judicial decisions \u2022 Writing and opinions of scholars &Commercial treaties and agreements Types of business enterprises: \u2022 Sole business concern \u2022 Partnership business organization \u2022 Company : a) Private b) Public Sole business:In this type of business organization, single person establishes, manages, organizes and control the whole business and also singly liable towards the profit and loss of the business."}{"question": "What is the definition of a partnership business?", "answer": "Voluntary origin and end Limitations of sole business: \u2022 Unlimited liability \u2022 Limited capital \u2022 Uncertain future \u2022 Absence of legal status \u2022 Chances of impractical decisions \u2022 Lack of specialization \u2022 Loss in absence of a key person Partnership business organization: In this type of business organization, more than one people join their hands to earn profit by investing collectively."}{"question": "What is the definition of a partnership business?", "answer": "Act 2053 regulates the incorporation of a company in Nepal."}{"question": "What is the definition of a company?", "answer": "Company is considered as an artificial legal person."}{"question": "What are the characteristics of a sole business?", "answer": "Characteristics of sole business: \u2022 Sole ownership \u2022 Sole management and control \u2022 Unlimited liability \u2022 Limited areas of operation \u2022 Less legal formalities?"}{"question": "What is the name of the company?", "answer": "It is registered under private registration act 2014."}{"question": "What are the characteristics of partnership business?", "answer": "Characteristics of partnership business: \u2022 Joint ownership \u2022 Unlimited liability \u2022 Sharing of profit and loss \u2022 Established on the basis of agreement between persons \u2022 Members do not have separate existence \u2022 Joint management and control \u2022 Joint agent slip \u2022 Partnership right cannot be transferred."}{"question": "What are the characteristics of a company?", "answer": "Company can be further divided into two as private limited company and public limited company."}{"question": "What is the legal name of the company?", "answer": "Ltd."}{"question": "What is the difference between Private company & Public company?", "answer": "\u2022 Legal artificial person \u2022 Perpetual existence \u2022 Limited liability \u2022 Common seal \u2022 Voluntary associations of persons \u2022 Capital collected by issuing shares \u2022 Transferability of shares \u2022 Management by representatives/effective management \u2022 Publication of financial statement \u2022 Unlimited capital \u2022 Public faith \u2022 Unlimited business capability Limitation of company business organization: \u2022 Difficulty in formation \u2022 Lack of personal interest \u2022 Lack of secrecy \u2022 Possibility of fraud \u2022 Exploitation of shareholders \u2022 Group formation for power \u2022 Conflict of interest \u2022 Absence of prompt decision \u2022 Lack of closeness Comparison between Private company & Public company S."}{"question": "What is the definition of asymmetric crypto system?", "answer": "N."}{"question": "What is the definition of asymmetric crypto?", "answer": "Nepal has enacted the electronic transactions act 2063 (ETA 2063), which comes into effective from December 8, 2006 and electronic transactions rules 2064(ETR 2064) also came into force in 2007."}{"question": "What is the name of the company?", "answer": "Subject matters Private company Public company 1 No."}{"question": "How many directors can be incorporated?", "answer": "of directors 1 Minimum 3 & maximum 11 directors 4 Article of association can use schedule I of company act Must have own 5 Offer of subscription of share / debenture Do not offer to subscribe Offer subscription to public to sell its shares & debentures 6 Transfer of share Cannot transfer Transfer easily 7 Legal formalities Less More 8 Publication of financial statement of trimester of each fiscal year Not required Must publish 9 Commencement of business After getting certificate of incorporation After getting the certificate of commencement of business 10 Financial strength Financially less strong Financially strong Cyber Law: Cyber law provides the legal framework related to the use of computer, information and communication and the governing technology."}{"question": "What is the definition of a cyber law?", "answer": "Therefore, it regulates the computer based activities including business (ecommerce) and the government (e-government)."}{"question": "What is the maximum number of shareholders?", "answer": "of Shareholders Minimum 1 Maximum 50 Minimum 7 Maximum no limit 2 Company naming pattern Pvt."}{"question": "What is the legal name of the company?", "answer": "Limited 3 No."}{"question": "What is the definition of asymmetric crypto system?", "answer": "Important terminology defined in ETA 2063 a) Asymmetric Crypto System \u2013 It is a system that creates a securedkey-pair consisting of a private key creating a digital signature and apublic key to verify the digital signature."}{"question": "What is a computer system?", "answer": "(g) Computer System - A device or a group of devices, containing allcomputer programmes including input and output support devices,electronic instructions, input and output data that performs logical,arithmetic, data storage and retrieval, communication includingcontrolling functions."}{"question": "What is a computer system?", "answer": "(c) Originator \u2013 It is a person who generates, stores or transmitselectronic records, and this term also includes a person who causes anyother person to carry out such functions:Provided that it shall not include an intermediary."}{"question": "what is a computer?", "answer": "(d) Computer- An electro-magnetic, optical or other high-speed dataprocessing device or system, which performs logical, arithmetic andmemory functions by manipulating electro-magnetic or optical impulses,and also includes all acts of input, output, processing, storage andcomputer software or communication facilities which are connected orrelated to the computer in any computer system or computer network."}{"question": "What is a license?", "answer": "(b) License- It is alicense obtained pursuant to Sub-section (3) ofSection 18."}{"question": "what is a computer?", "answer": "(e) Computer Database - An information, knowledge and concept orpresentation of instructions, which are being prepared or have alreadybeen prepared in word, image, voice or audio visual form in aformalized manner or which have been produced by a computer,computer system or computer network, with a view to use in acomputer, computer system or computer network."}{"question": "What is a key pair?", "answer": "(j) Key Pair - A private key in an asymmetric crypto system and ofpair of public key, interconnected in a mathematics form with theprivate key which has a code to verify digital signature by the public keyto be created from the private key."}{"question": "What is a computer system?", "answer": "(k) Data - The presentation of information, knowledge, fact andconcept or instructions in any form, which are kept in a formalizedmanner in a computer system or computer network and is intended forprocessing the same, or processed or stored in a computer memory."}{"question": "What is a certificate?", "answer": "(i) Subscriber - A person who has obtained a certificate under Subsection(3) of Section 31."}{"question": "What is a computer?", "answer": "(h) Computer Resource - A computer, computer system, computernetwork, data, computer database or software."}{"question": "What is a computer network?", "answer": "(f) Computer Network- An interrelationship between two or morethan two computers having interconnection with each other or in contactof communication."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(t) Certifying Authority- A certifying authority which has obtaineda license to issue a Digital Signature Certificate under Sub-section (3) ofSection 18."}{"question": "Who is appointed or designated to sign the digital signature?", "answer": "(n) Controller - The Controller appointed or designated pursuant tosection 13."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(r) Certificate - A Digital Signature Certificate issued by theCertifying Authority under Section 30."}{"question": "What is the name of the tribunal?", "answer": "(q) Appellate Tribunal - The Information Technology AppellateTribunal formed pursuant to section 66."}{"question": "What is a certification practice statement?", "answer": "(s) Certification Practice Statement - Any statement issued by aCertifying Authority to specify the practices to be applied by theCertifying Authority while issuing a Digital Signature Certificate."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(w) Electronic Form - A form of information transmitted, received orstored by generating the same through the means of magnetic, optical,computer memory or similar other devices."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(p) Access - An opportunity of gaining entry into, logical,arithmetical or resources of memory function of any computer,computer system or computer network, giving instructions to suchresources or making communication contact with such resources."}{"question": "What is the definition of a digital signature?", "answer": "(u) Addressee -A person receiving the processed electronic record asintended by the originator."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(m) Private Key - A key of any key pair used to create a digitalsignature."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(v) Electronic Record - The data, record, image or sound transmitted,received or stored in an electronic form by generating the same throughany means."}{"question": "What is the name of the tribunal?", "answer": "(l) Tribunal - The Information Technology Tribunal formed pursuantto section 60."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(x) Public Key - A key of any key pair used to verify digitalsignature."}{"question": "What is a digital signature?", "answer": "(o) Digital Signature - A signature made in any electronic form to beincluded in the transformation of electronic record by a person having anon- transformed initial electronic record and the public key of signatoryby using a type of asymmetric crypto system that may clearly ascertainthe following matters: (1) Whether or not transformation of electronic record wascreated by using a type of private key keeping a logical consistency withthe public key of signatory; and (2) Whether or not the initial electronic record has beenchanged after the transformation of electronic record."}{"question": "What is the definition of a digital signature?", "answer": "Provided that it shall not include an intermediary."}{"question": "What is the definition of information?", "answer": "(y) Information - The data details of the scripted texts, images,sounds, codes, computer programmes, software and computer databases."}{"question": "what is a computer accessory?", "answer": "(ab) Computer Accessory \u2013 It is a technology such as computer resource,the information used by any institution in its business, a software-likeitem produced or purchased by such an institution, hardware andcomputer network."}{"question": "What is the definition of information system?", "answer": "(z) Information system - A system to generate, produce, transmit,receive, store and display information or to process the same by othermethod."}{"question": "What is the definition of computer hardware?", "answer": "(aa) Software- Any specific part of computer system such as systemsoftware and application software having the capacity for operatingcomputer hardware."}